Guide to the John Chardin Correspondence and Documents
Beinecke Rare Book and Manuscript Library
John Chardin correspondence and documents
1671-1719
GEN MSS 216
Beinecke Rare Book and Manuscript Library
3.62
(5 boxes and 1 portfolio)
Correspondence, manuscript accounts, printed bills of lading completed in manuscript, and other manuscript documents of Sir John Chardin, his wife, Lady Chardin, his brother, Daniel Chardin, and others. Most letters and documents are bound in volumes; also present are a few unbound items. Many letters and documents relate to India and the East India Company, including items concerning Thomas Pitt, Elihu Yale, Alvarez de Fonseca, and Nicolo Manuchi. Accompanied by brief notes of a former owner.
Chardin, John, Sir, 1643-1713
Immediate Source of Acquisition
Gift of William Sloane, 1921.
Conditions Governing Access
The materials are open for research.
Existence and Location of Copies
This collection is available on microfilm; however, it was filmed prior to the current arrangement. All materials described are present, but they appear on microfilm in the order listed in Notes of a former owner, located in box 3, folder 23.
BIOGRAPHICAL NOTE
John Chardin, 1643-1713, was born in Paris and travelled in the Near East as a merchant and jeweller. He later settled in England and was an agent to the East India Company. Chardin was the author of Journal du voyage du chevalier Chardin en Perse & aux Indes Orientales, par la Mer Noire & par la Colchide (1686).
Scope and Contents
The John Chardin Correspondence and Documents consist of correspondence, accounts, bills of lading, and other documents by or pertaining to John Chardin, his wife, Lady Chardin, and his brother, Daniel Chardin. Many papers relate to India and the East India Company, including letters and documents concerning Thomas Pitt, Elihu Yale, Alvarez de Fonseca, and Nicolo Manuchi. The collection is accompanied by brief notes of a former owner.
The collection is housed in five boxes and one portfolio and is organized into two series: Unbound Letters and Documents and Bound Volumes. Boxes 4-5 and the portfolio contain oversize material.
Folder titles enclosed in quotation marks were transcribed from volume spines. Descriptive notes for single documents and volumes were taken from descriptions prepared by a former owner. These notes may not fully represent the contents of an item. For example, volumes titled "letters" or "correspondence" may also contain bills of lading, accounts, or other documents. Most volumes contain items relating to Daniel Chardin and Lady Chardin, as well as John Chardin.
Great Britain -- Commerce -- India; India -- Commerce -- Great Britain; Chardin, Daniel; Chardin, John, Sir, 1643-1713; Chardin, Lady; Fonseca, Alvarez de; Manuchi, Nicolo; Pitt, Thomas, 1653-1726; Yale, Elihu, 1649-1721; East India Company; Phillipps, Thomas, Sir, 1792-1872 -- Ownership
- Unbound Letters and Documents, 1686-1701/2; Series I; 0.2; (.5 boxes)
  - Bills of lading, 1686 (Box 1, Folder 1)
    Scope and Contents
    Four bills for specie, consigned by Sir John Chardin, "Alvaro Du Costa," John Mendez da Costa, and Francisco Salvador to Elihu Yale, in the ship Williamson, Capt. Richard Warner, signed by the latter
  - Bill of lading, 1687 Apr 11 (Box 1, Folder 2)
    One bill for specie, consigned by John Cholmly to Elihu Yale, in the ship Resolution, Capt. William Sharp, signed by the latter
  - Bills of lading, 1687/88 Feb 13 (Box 1, Folder 3)
    Two bills for specie, consigned by John Mendez da Costa and Francis Salvador to Elihu Yale, in the ship Defence, Capt. William Heath, signed by J. Foster
  - Bill of lading, 1687/88 Feb 15 (Box 1, Folder 4)
    One bill for "Corrall Beads," consigned by Petter and Pierre Henrriques to Elihu Yale, in the ship Defence, Capt. William Heath, signed by J. Foster
  - Account of Elihu Yale with Thomas Pitt and Daniel Chardin, 1699/1700 Mar 13 (Box 1, Folder 5)
    "Elihu Yale, Esq., his acctt. currtt. adjusted this day with Thos. Pitt Esq, and Mr. Danl. Chardin"
  - AL, draft, to William Gifford and Elihu Yale, 1686 Dec 31 (Box 1, Folder 6)
    Rough draft of a letter to the "Honble Wm. Gifford Esq," and "Mr. Elihu Yalle," relating to the shipment of 4 chests of silver Also the original bill of lading relating to this shipment
  - LS to Daniel Chardin, 1697 Apr 24 (Box 1, Folder 7)
    In French, 19 pages, signed by Sir John Chardin, with two references to "Mr. Yealle"
  - LS to Daniel Chardin, 1700 Jan 2 (Box 1, Folder 8)
    In French, 16 pages, signed by Sir John Chardin (Phillipps MS 16850)
  - LS to Daniel Chardin, 1701 Sep 20 (Box 1, Folder 9)
    In French, 10 pages, signed by Sir John Chardin
  - LS to Daniel Chardin, 1701/2 Jan 15 (Box 1, Folder 10)
    In French, 8 pages, signed by Sir John Chardin, with a reference to "la pierre brutte par Yeale"
  - LS to Daniel Chardin, n.d. (Box 1, Folder 11)
    In French, 6 pages, signed by Sir John Chardin
- Bound Volumes, 1671-1719; Series II; 0.84; (2.5 boxes and 1 portfolio)
  - "Sir John Chardin's Letters", 1686-1706 (Box 1, Folder 12-13)
    Sir John Chardin's letters to his brother Daniel, 2 vols. Includes 16 letters in French; an agreement between the two brothers in French, signed by them both, and sealed 19 Nov 1686; and other papers (Phillipps MS 16850, 16851)
  - "Sir John Chardin's Letters", 1681-1718 (Box 1, Folder 14)
    73 letters and other documents, mostly written in French Includes an ALS, dated 3 Feb 1686/7, written in French, and addressed to "Mr. Daniel Chardin in ye ship Williamson now att Anchor att Deale bond for East India" (Phillipps MS 16854)
  - "Sir John Chardin's Correspondence", 1690-1718
    58 letters, etc., relating to the East India Trade (Phillipps MS 16849)
  - "Chardin Correspondence", 1695-1719 (Box 1, Folder 15)
    82 letters and other documents, written mostly in French (Phillipps MS 17116)
  - "Chardin Mercantile Correspondence", 1687-1719 (Box 2, Folder 16)
    Foreign correspondence; 40 letters written in French (Phillipps MS 17114)
  - "Sir John Chardin's Papers", 1671-1718
    9 pieces, including a vellum document dated 17 March 1671, relating to Antoine Chardin and Daniel Chardin (Phillipps MS 16847, 17365)
  - "Sir John Chardin's Papers", 1687-1717
    60 pieces, including several statements of account signed by Thomas Pitt. Letters, etc., many of which are written in French (Phillipps MS 16848)
  - "Sir John Chardin's East India Papers", 1688-1718 (Box 2, Folder 17)
    72 pieces Includes a letter from Thomas Marshall, dated St. Hellena, 12 August 1706, referring to 2 ships being carried out of the road on the 1st of June, by the French Accompanied by photocopies of brief descriptions of some of the contents, written in an unidentified hand (Phillipps MS 16852)
  - "Chardin Bills of Lading", 1682-1718 (Box 2, Folder 18)
    Daniel Chardin, Merchant of Fort St. George; 28 bills of lading and 8 Bills of Exchange (Phillipps MS 16855)
  - "Lady Chardin and Daniel Chardin, Correspondence from Pondicherry, Paris, La Haye, &c, &c", 1685-1719 (Box 2, Folder 19)
    93 pieces, mostly written in French, including several by Sir John Chardin (Phillipps MS 17115)
  - "Bills and Letters of Lady Chardin", 1709-18 (Box 2, Folder 20)
    40 bills and letters (Phillipps MS 16853)
  - "Chardin Receipts", 1681-1718 (Box 3, Folder 21)
    60 receipted accounts, etc., of Lady Chardin and others (Phillipps MS 16856)
  - "Hebert's letters from Pondicherry, 1708, &c", 1708-18 (Box 3, Folder 22)
    21 letters written in French (Phillipps MS 17117)
  - Notes of a former owner, n.d. (Box 3, Folder 23)
- Oversize, 2.58; (2 boxes and 1 portfolio)
  - "Sir John Chardin's Correspondence" (in Series II), 1690-1718 (Box 4 (Oversize), Folder 24)
  - "Sir John Chardin's Papers" (in Series II), 1687-1717 (Box 5 (Oversize), Folder 25)
  - "Sir John Chardin's Papers" (in Series II) (Box Port, folder 26)